this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
the Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter 5 The Rescue of the Tin
Woodman When Dorothy awoke the sun was shining through the trees and Toto had
long been out chasing birds around him and squirrels.
She sat up and looked around her Scarecrow, still standing patiently in
his corner, waiting for her. “We must go and search for water,” she said to him. “Why
do you want water?” he asked. “To wash my face clean after the dust of the road,
and to drink, so the dry bread will not stick in my throat.”
“It must be inconvenient to be made of flesh,” said the Scarecrow thoughtfully
free must sleep, and eat and drink.
However, you have brains, and it is worth a lot of bother to be able to think
properly.” They left the cottage and walked through the trees until they
found the little spring of clear water, where Dorothy drank and bathed and ate
her breakfast. She saw there was not much bread left in the basket, and the girl
was thankful the Scarecrow did not have to eat anything, for there was scarcely
enough for herself and Toto for the day.
When she had finished her meal, and was about to go back to the road of yellow
brick, she was startled to hear a deep groan nearby What was that?” she asked
timidly. “I cannot imagine,” replied the Scarecrow; “but we can go and see.” Just
then another groan reached their ears, and the sound seemed to come from behind
them. They turned and walked through the forest a few steps, when Dorothy
discovered something shining an array of sunshine that fell between the trees. She
ran to the place and then stopped short, with a little cry of surprise. One of the
big trees had been partially chopped through, and standing beside it, with an
uplifted axe in his hand was a man made entirely of ten His head and arms and
legs were jointed upon his body, but he stood perfectly motionless,
as if he could not stir at all. Dorothy looked at him in amazement, and so did
the Scarecrow, while Toto barked sharply and made a snap at the ten legs, which
hurt his teeth. “Did you groan?” asked Dorothy. “Yes,” answered the ten man, “I did.
I’ve been groaning for more than a year, and no one has ever heard me before or
come to help me can I do for you?” she inquired softly, for she was moved by the
sad voice in which the man spoke. “Get an oil can and oil my joints,” he answered.
“They are all rusted so badly that I cannot move them at all; if I am well
oiled I shall soon be all right again.
You will find an oil can on a shelf in my cottage.” Dorothy at once ran back to
the cottage and found the oil can and then she returned and asked anxiously,
“Where are your joints?” “Oil my neck, first,” replied the Tin Woodman though she it,
and as it was quite badly rusted that Scarecrow took a hold of the tin head
and moved it gently from side to side until it worked freely, and then the man
could turn it himself. “Now oil the joints in my arms,” he said. And Dorothy oiled
them and the Scarecrow bent them carefully until they were quite free
from rust and as good as new.
The Tin Woodman gave a sigh of satisfaction and lowered his axe, which
he leaned against the tree. “This is a great comfort,” he said. “I have been
holding that axe in the air ever since I
rusted, and I’m glad to be able to put it
down at last. Now, if you will oil the joints of my legs, I shall be all right
once more.” So the oiled his legs until he could move them freely; and he thanked
them again and again for his release, for he seemed a very polite creature, and very grateful.
“I might have stood there always if you had not come along,” he said; “so you have
certainly saved my life.
How did you happen to be here?” “We are on
our way to the Emerald City to see the Great Oz,” she answered, “and we stopped at
your cottage to pass the night.” “Why do you wish to see Oz?” he asked. “I want him
to send me back to Kansas, and the Scarecrow wants him to put a few
brains into his head,” she replied. The Tin Woodman appeared to think deeply for a
moment. Then he said you suppose ours could give me a heart?” “Why, I guess so,”
Dorothy answered. “It would be as easy as to give the Scarecrow brains.” “True,” the
Tin Woodman returned. “So, if you will allow me to join your party, I will also
go to the Emerald City and ask Oz to help me.” “Come along,” said that Scarecrow
heartedly and Dorothy added that she would be pleased to have his company. So
the Tin Woodman shouldered his axe and they all passed through the forest until
they came to the road that was paved with yellow brick. The Tin Woodman had
asked Dorothy to put the oil can in her basket. “For,” he said, “if I should get
caught in the rain the rust again and I would need the oil can badly.” It was a
bit of good luck to have their new comrade join the party, for soon after
they had begun their journey again they came to a place where the trees and
branches grew so thick over the road that the travelers could not pass. But
the Tin Woodman set to work with his axe and chopped so well that soon he cleared
a passage for the entire party. Dorothy was thinking so earnestly as they walked
along that she did not notice when the Scarecrow stumbled into a hole and
rolled over to the side of the road.
Indeed he was obliged to call to her to help him up again. “Why didn’t you walk
around the hole?” asked the Tin Woodman. “I don’t know enough,” replied the Scarecrow
cheerfully. “My head is stuffed with straw, you know, and that is why I am going to
Oz to ask him for some brains.” “Oh, I see,” said the Tin Woodman. “But, after all,
brains are not the best things in the world.” “Have you any?” inquired the
Scarecrow. “No, my head is quite empty,” answered the Woodman. “But once I had
brains, and a heart also; so, having tried them both, I would much
rather have a heart.” “And why is that?” asked the Scarecrow. “I will tell you my
story, and then you No So, while they were walking through the forest, the Tin Woodman told the
following story: “I was born the son of a woodman who chopped down trees in the
forest and sold the wood for a living.
When I grew up, I too became a woodchopper and after my father died I took care of
my old mother as long as she lived. Then I made up my mind that instead of living
alone I would marry, so that I might not become lonely. “There was one of the
Munchkin girls who was so beautiful that I soon grew to love her with all my
heart. She, on her part, promised to marry me as soon as I can earn enough money to
build a better house for her; so I said to work harder than ever. But the girl
lived with an old woman who did not want her to marry anyone, for she was so lazy
she wished the girl to remain with her and do the cooking and the housework. So
the old woman went to the Wicked Witch of the East, and promised her to sheep
and a cow if she would prevent the marriage. Thereupon the Wicked Witch
enchanted my axe, and when I was chopping away at my best one day, for I was
anxious to get the new house and my wife as soon as possible, the axe slipped all
at once and cut off my left leg. “This at first seemed a great misfortune, for I
knew a one-legged man could not do very well as a woodchopper So I went to a
tinsmith and had him make me a new leg out of ten The leg worked very well, once
I was used to it. But my action angered the Wicked Witch of the East, for she
promised the old woman I should not marry the pretty Munchkin girl. When I
began chopping again, my axe slipped and cut off my right leg. Again I went to the
tinsmith, and again he made me a leg out of ten
After this the enchanted axe cut off my arms, one after the other; but, nothing
daunted, I had them replaced with ten ones. The Wicked Witch then made the axe
slip and cut off my head, and at first I thought that was the end of me.
But the tinsmith happened to come along, and he made me a new head out of ten I
thought I had beaten the Wicked Witch then, and I worked harder than ever; but I
little knew how cruel my enemy could be.
She thought of a new way to kill my love for the beautiful Munchkin maiden, and
made my axe slip again, so that it cut right through my body, splitting me into two halves.
Once more the tinsmith came to my help and made me a body of ten fastening my
ten arms and legs and head to it, by means of joints, so that I could move
around as well as ever. But, alas! I had
now no heart, so that I lost all my love for the Munchkin girl, and did not care
whether I married her or not. I suppose she is still living with the old woman,
waiting for me to come after her. “My body shone so brightly in the sun that I felt
very proud of it and it did not matter to me now if my
axe slipped, for it could not cut me.
There was only one danger— —that my joints would rust; but I kept an oil can in my
cottage and took care to oil myself whenever I needed it. However, there came
a day when I forgot to do this, and, being caught in a rainstorm, before I thought
of the danger my joints had rusted, and I was left to stand in the woods until you
came to help me. It was a terrible thing to undergo during that year I stood
there I had time to think of the greatest loss I had known was loss of my
heart. While I was in love I was the happiest man on earth;
but no one can love who has not a heart,
and so I am resolved to ask Oz to give
me one. If he does, I will go back to the Munchkin maiden and marry her well
Dorothy and the Scarecrow had been greatly interested in the story of the
Tin Woodman, and now they knew why he was so anxious to get a new heart. “All the
same,” said the Scarecrow, “I shall ask for brains instead of a heart; for a fool
would not know what to do with a heart if he had one.” “I shall take the heart,”
returned the Tin Woodman; “for brains do not make one happy, and happiness is the
best thing in the world.” Dorothy did not say anything where she
was puzzled to know which of her two friends was right, and she decided if she
could only get back to Kansas and Aunt Em, it did not matter so much whether the
Woodman had no brains and the Scarecrow no heart, or each got what they wanted.
What worried her most was that the bread was nearly gone, and another meal for
herself and Toto would empty the basket.
To be sure, neither the Woodman nor the Scarecrow ever ate anything, but she was
not made of tin Nora straw, and she could not live unless she
was fed The end of chapter five this is